Good morning. So today's דף *daf* is כ"ד *Chaf Dalet*, 24, and
we pick up right at the very bottom of דף כ"ג *Daf
Chaf Gimmel* עמוד ב' *Amud Bet* at the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. And
now we start discussing some of the specifics about what the moon
will look like when it's a new moon and testing the witnesses
and verifying whether what they said was even possible, let alone that
what one testimony would correspond to another testimony. So the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says the following: היינו לפני החמה Hainu lifnei hachamma, היינו לצפונה
hainu litzfona. היינו לאחר החמה היינו לדרומה hainu lidroma. *Hainu lifnei hachammah
hainu litzfonah, hainu leachar hachammah hainu ledromah*. So the first question that
was asked, let me just erase some of this, was did you
see the new moon before or after the sun. So to remind
us, okay, this is
the
old moon.
Right? The moon moves counterclockwise relative to the sun. So the moon
moves when it went here exactly lined up, what's that called again,
congruence?
Conjunction. When it's in conjunction exactly lined up, that's completely dark because
only the back of the moon is getting illuminated. So the old
moon is just a little bit off from in line with the
sun and then it moves counterclockwise and then when it's visible as
the new moon, when it moves off the exact conjunction,
then did I say that right again? Okay, off the exact conjunction,
that's the מולד *Molad*, but it's only visible a number of hours
later when it's separate enough from the sun that it's not being
blinded by the sun. And then it will be visible, it will
be behind the sun. So the old moon is visible at the
very end of night, right? Because it's right before sunrise. You see?
Because it'll be in front and then after sunrise then it'll be
too bright, you won't see. And then at the end of the
day, it'll set before the sun. So the old moon is visible
right before sunrise, and the new moon is the opposite. By the
new moon, you've got that the moon has moved just behind the
sun, so after sunrise you can't see it, it's too bright, but
you will see it after sunset because the sun will have set
and then the moon will be trailing behind. Okay, so that's the
new moon. So the new moon is seen, so the question was
whether did you see it before the sun or after the sun.
And the answer has to be after the sun. Okay, that's why
the משנה Mishnah, *Mishnah* says כל האומר לפני החמה לא אמר כלום
lo amar klum, *Kol ha'omer lifnei hachammah lo amar klum*. But now
we have another question, which is it says to the north or
to the south. Now, to the north or to the south doesn't
seem so relevant to us, but if you look at it a
little bit differently, okay, the ArtScroll actually has a very nice picture
here. Okay, here's the person, okay, and if you think about this
as again, don't look at this as over him, like this is
the horizon, okay, this is the east, this is the west, this
is the north, this is the south. Okay, so a sun will
go from the east to the west, but the sun actually in
the northern hemisphere goes on an angle, sort of like the angle
of the sun is towards the south. So
in the equinox, it's rising in the east, going towards the south,
and setting in the west. Okay, in the
winter, its path is shorter, so in the winter its path looks
like this. Okay, is that clear? Right? It goes more, starts more
from the southeast, sets in the southwest. In the summer, its path
is longer, so it goes more like that, whoops, and like that,
okay, and sets more the northwest. Okay, so anyway, so we are
asking now, was it to the south or the north? But if
you view actually, this would be a little bit more relevant to
what we're going to say a second from now, but just keep
in mind, anyway, if you view the sun going here, to say
is it to the south or the north, actually this is a
little bit for the next גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, I'm sorry about that,
but anyway,
so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says,
let me just read that again. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says היינו
לפני החמה היינו לצפונה *Hainu lifnei hachammah hainu litzfonah*. So in front
of the חמה *Hammah* is north because since it heads, here, this
will be easier for this part, we'll go back in a minute.
Since it goes from the east to the west, but it goes
towards the south, okay, it goes towards the south, rising in the
east, setting in the west, goes to the south. So לפני החמה
*Lifnei hachammah*, this is what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, היינו לצפונה
*Hainu litzfonah* is the north. Because after it set, it's heading towards
maybe this is a better picture, I'm sort of going to ruin
this. But if this is east and west, north, south, so it
sort of goes like that, okay? Right? If you can sort of
imagine it going in that direction. So if it is לפני החמה
*Lifnei hachammah*, in front of the חמה *Hammah*, it's more northern. If
it's behind the חמה *Hammah*, it's more southern since it's going towards
the south. Is that clear? Like maybe that's easy looking at it.
If it's going from the east to the south and then setting
in the west, so in front of the חמה *Hammah* is more
to the north and behind the חמה *Hammah* is more to the
south. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* just says. Yeah, that'll come, this'll
come up in a minute. So the גמרא Gemara. says, "I don't
get why it's a difference before-after versus north-south." היינו לפני החמה, היינו
לצפונה. In front of the moon is more towards the north because
as it sets, after it sets, it's going more northernly. היינו לאחר
חמה, Hainu leachar chamma, היינו לדרומה. lidroma
Behind the moon is to the south because it's, you know, it's
coming from the south and going towards the north. So אמר אביי.
amar Abaye. So אביי Abaye says, "No, the question of before and
after is not is it trailing or is it leading. That's one
question, and there the answer has to be that it's trailing. It's
actually a different question." אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, "פגימתה לפני החמה או
לאחר החמה? pegimata lifnei hachamma o leachar hachamma? Is
its lacking, its indentation, before or after?" Now, this is actually quite
easy, right? Because the way you see the moon, right, right, here's
the sun. Which part gets illuminated? The part that gets illuminated, right?
I mean, if it's direct in the line, you're not seeing it
because only that gets illuminated. But once it gets a little bit
off, right, the line, then, you know, then this part gets illuminated,
and you see the sliver, you don't see the whole thing, right?
I mean, actually, right, all of that gets illuminated, but you're only
able to see that, you know, you're only able to see that,
so you get to see a sliver like that. But anyway, so
but here's the right point. Now, but here's the point, though. Here's
the point, which is, relative to the sun, right, it has to
be like this because it's only this part that is getting illuminated.
Right, the lacking can't be facing the sun. The part that is,
the part, it's always the lit part that is facing the sun
and the lacking that's away because it's always getting lit by the
sun. Okay, so that's what the גמרא Gemara says. So it says,
אם אמר פגימתה לפני החמה או לאחר חמה, im amar pegimata lifnei
hachamma o leachar chamma, נחמי אם אמר לפני החמה, nachamei im amar
lifnei hachamma, if he says the lacking was the part facing the
sun, the indentation, לא אמר כלום, lo amar klum, that can't be
true. דאמר רבי יוחנן, Damar Rabbi Yochanan, מאי דכתיב המשל ופחד עמו
עשה שלום במרומיו? mai dichtiv hamshal ufachad imo oseh shalom bimromav?
"Dominion and fear is with Him; He makes peace in the supernal
realms." מעולם לא ראתה חמה פגימתה של לבנה. Me'olam lo rata chamma
pegimata shel levana.
The sun never saw the indentation, the lacking of the moon. ולא
פגימתה של קשת, Velo pegimata shel keshet, and not the indentation of
the rainbow. פגימתה של לבנה דחלשה דעתה. Pegimata shel levana dechalsha da'ata.
The lacking of the moon because it would become despondent, despair, presumably
the moon would become despondent. You know, the whole מדרש Midrash that
the moon wanted to be equal to the sun and it got
minimized. So it's not enough that I'm smaller than the sun, but
now the sun gets to see my, like, nakedness, gets to see
my, you know, my lacking? So you can't, so the part that's
missing is always facing away, or else the moon is going to
be too embarrassed. פגימתה של קשת, Pegimata shel keshet,
and it never saw the indentation of the rainbow, דלא לימרו עובדי
חמה, delo limru ovdei chamma, that the worshippers of the sun should
not say, גירי קא משדייא, girei ka mashdaya, "He's shooting arrows."
Because, right, this is what a rainbow looks like. Now if you
think of a rainbow as a bow, right, you
shoot the arrows from facing the indentation. Which by the way is
the reason רמב"ן Ramban says, you know, when it says זאת אות
קשתי נתתי בענן והיה לאות ברית ביני ובין הארץ, zot ot kashti
natati be'anan vehayta le'ot brit beini uvein ha'aretz,
what is the סימן siman of the rainbow? The סימן siman of
the rainbow is that when you, like, surrender, you, like, hold your
rainbow, like, you hold your archer's bow in the reverse. Right? It's
like, you know, if you hand over your gun, like, you hand
it over this way. So God is essentially saying to the earth,
like He's flipping over the bow, like, "I'm not going to shoot
down at you," you know? That's the symbolism the רמב"ן Ramban says.
So here the point that the sun, now I don't know what
it means that the sun never saw that. If that means that
there can't be a rainbow and the sun can't be situated somewhere
here in the rainbow, somebody would have to tell me if that's
true or not. But if what it means is that usually the,
you know, the rainbow appears in the sky lower than the, I
mean, if it means like the sun is always here, right, so
then the sun is never using the rainbow because it's always flipped
the opposite direction to be able to be used. And if the
rainbow were like this, so then the sun would be shooting, could
be shooting arrows down at us. Okay, so somebody will have to
find out whether that is true or not, whether the sun is
always higher than the arc of the rainbow. I don't know, I
have no idea why it's דווקא davka should be true.
All I know is I never realized, I never made this connection,
that the raindrops of the מבול Mabul are the arrows.
Hmm, that's a good... I didn't make that connection either, but that
could be. Yeah,
that... right, right. So anyway, somebody will tell, will look up about
the relationship of the sun to where rainbows are. But anyway, the
basic point is that now we're saying two things: the moon always
has to be behind the sun, which would be according to this
way of describing it, to the south of the sun, number one.
And the lacking of the moon would always have to be behind
the sun as well. Okay, so that's אי אמר לפני החמה, ei
amar lifnei hachamma, if you were to claim that the lacking was
facing the sun,
לא אמר כלום, lo amar klum, because obviously it doesn't.
How high was it off the horizon? Which way was it pointing?
תנא חדא לצפונה דבריו קיימין. Tana chada litzfona devarav kayamin. If somebody
says,
now this doesn't exactly seem to be explicating the משנה, Mishnah but
okay, let's do it. If it is to the north, the moon,
then it's
legitimate. לדרומה to the south, לא אמר כלום, he did not say
anything. Now that's hard to understand because again, the way we just
understood it, if you're going to describe where it is trailing, we
have to say it's to the south of the sun. I understand.
Wait a minute, let's, okay. הא תניא איפכא, ha tanya ipcha, did
we have it, anyway, it doesn't matter, we're going to have a
contradiction, we have a ברייתא Baraita that says the opposite. לדרומה דבריו
קיימין, lidroma devarav kayamin, to the south it makes sense. לצפונה לא
אמר כלום, litzfona lo amar klum, to the north it's not valid.
Now that at least works in terms of how we've been describing
it here, but anyway,
here you have a contradiction. So how are you going to resolve
it?
So לא קשיא, lo kashya, it's not difficult. כאן בימות החמה כאן
בימות הגשמים. kan bimot hachama kan bimot hageshamim. It matters whether it
is the summer or the winter. Now what does that mean? So
Rashi has an explanation that doesn't exactly, it's not complicated, but it
doesn't exactly work astronomically. The best explanation is המאירי, haMeiri, which basically,
and now you see why I use this chart. Okay, so it
rises in the east, goes to the south and sets in the
west. Okay, but in the winter it is a smaller arc, there's
less daylight. So it rises in the southeast and sets in the
southwest. That's in the winter. In the, that's this,
this one here. In the summer, okay, in the summer, it's longer
and it rises in the northeast and sets in the northwest. So
the way המאירי haMeiri reads it, the question is where did the
moon set, where on the horizon? So one says you have to
say it set in the north. The other says he have to
say that the moon set in the south of the horizon. לא
קשיא, lo kashya, it depends if it's the winter or if it's
the summer. If it's the winter, it'll set in the south. If
it's the summer, it'll set in the north. Okay, and that's the
way המאירי haMeiri reads it and we are not going to try
to unpack Rashi's explanation which is much more difficult.
This is relative to ירושלים? Yerushalayim?
Yeah, I mean, so for a person seeing it in ירושלים. Yerushalayim.
Yeah. Now by the way, the aspect of ירושלים Yerushalayim is interesting
because as I mentioned yesterday, the previous משנה mishnah, said חצר גדולה
היתה בירושלים, chatzer gedola hayta biYerushalayim, right? And calls and mentioned Rabban
Gamliel הזקן, HaZaken, right? So when there was a בית המקדש Beit
HaMikdash it was all taking place in
ירושלים, Yerushalayim, right? But as we're going to see in a minute,
post בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash it also took place in יבנה. Yavneh.
And we're going to see Rabban Gamliel not הזקן HaZaken and we're
going to talk about it being in יבנה. Yavneh. We had the
whole earlier story about Rabbi Akiva holding the witnesses up in לוד
Lod where clearly they were on their way to יבנה. Yavneh. So
it's really basically, it's wherever the witnesses saw. So if you're accepting
testimony in לוד Lod and you have to accept it within 24
hours, it really would be based on the line of sight of
anybody within 24 hours of לוד. Lod.
24 hours of walking, right?
Well no, they could go by horse.
Go by, okay,
yeah, you know, yeah.
I wanted to understand yesterday was if this all taking place in
some חצר ירושלים chatzer Yerushalayim and doesn't the pronouncement have to be
in the סנהדרין Sanhedrin in the בית המקדש? Beit HaMikdash? Doesn't the
קידוש החודש Kiddush HaChodesh really wherever they are? Yeah. Yeah. Actually
do they have members of the סנהדרין Sanhedrin though in?
Yeah, we'll discuss, the גמרא Gemara here does not refer to, discuss
in so much detail what exactly is the, you know, who exactly
is on the בית דין Beit Din for קידוש החודש. Kiddush HaChodesh.
That gets discussed in the beginning of the first פרק perek of
סנהדרין, Sanhedrin, but it does not have to be, you know, you
need like the נשיא Nasi and you need whatever, but it doesn't
exactly have to be, I mean it's true, they can't just say
any self-appointed בית דין Beit Din because obviously it needs to be
the central בית דין. Beit Din. But if I remember correctly, it
obviously has to be sort of like constituted by the נשיא, Nasi,
but I don't think that they actually technically be members of the
סנהדרין. Sanhedrin. Because anyway, they did קידוש החודש Kiddush HaChodesh for hundreds
of years after the חורבן בית Churban Bayit and after the disbandment
of the סנהדרין. Sanhedrin. So yes.
I understand the shapes and the and the dark side of the
moon bit, but where's the position of the moon if you see
a full moon like ערב יום טוב? erev Yom Tov?
Where will you see, what time of night?
I don't know, how can you draw, like the?
The full moon you will see, you'll see a full moon, it'll
always be, right, it should always be
like opposite.
Logically, logically you should see it and somebody,
so
when the, I'll just draw this very quickly. Okay, so the full
moon will be when it's exactly opposite the sun.
Okay, so here the sun is setting and the moon is rising,
right? And then that's why that's a full moon because you get
the entire side right illuminated. So therefore you will see a full
moon, at least in theory, that's the time not only is it
full but that it's visible the entire night. The sun sets, the
moon rises, right? It's halfway through the month, so it's exactly halfway
away from the from the sun. And then as the sun rises,
the moon sets. Okay, so when you see a full moon, it
should be in theory visible the whole night.
Right, it was a stupid question though, so when the sun sets,
right, so it's on the other side of the, it's on the
other side of the earth from where you are.
Yeah, not.
I mean the sun is always where it is, okay. The sun
is here, but the moon has moved from being here which it
is at the beginning of the month. Right, the moon goes around
the earth, right, in a month. So the moon is the thing
that travels. So the moon is here. Now as the earth is
turning towards the east and it's sunrise, right, so let's say imagine
you're here, right? So you've now turned and it's now sunrise, you
can't see the moon at all. Right? Now the earth continues to
turn and now you're turning away fully and it's sunset, and now
you see the moon that is fully illuminated by the sun and
you're seeing the full moon, which is what that was
except the earth's a titchy bit of the sun so it doesn't
matter it's night right exactly.
All right. All right, let's keep on going. All right. תנו רבנן,
Tanu Rabbanan, let's move on,
all right, let's do that. תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. אחד אומר גבוה
שתי מרדאות ואחד אומר שלש עדותן קיימת. echad omer gavoah shtei marda'ot
ve'echad omer shalosh edutan kayamet.
Now
how about just describing like where it is in the sky? If
some say that it's like two מרדאות marda'ot which is like I
don't know saddles higher than the horizon and the other says three,
so again like how precise are you expecting them to be? Then
actually those are considered to be testifying to the same thing. We
allow for a little imprecision. אחד אומר שלש ואחד אומר חמש. echad
omer shalosh ve'echad omer chamesh. This might also remind you of other
cases in סנהדרין Sanhedrin about what hour something took place. If one
says three and one says five, that's too much, assuming too much
imprecision, and therefore עדותן בטלה. edutan beteila. They are negated, meaning you
cannot say that they're testifying to the same thing. אבל מצטרפין לעדות
אחרת. aval mitztarfin l'edut acheret. You won't say that any one of
them is definitely lying and they could combine for another testimony. רש״י
Rashi says what that means. It becomes a little bit interesting how
this works out with other discussions in סנהדרין. Sanhedrin. I'll just tell
you רש״י Rashi says it means that if another witness comes and
says three, then he can work with the guy that said three.
And another one says five, he can work with the guy that
said five. These guys are not, you know, they're not- we can't
assume- they're not- they're not false witnesses, you know,
but one of them obviously clearly is not saying the same thing
as the other. You don't know which. Each one retains their חזקה
chazaka of being כשר kasher and therefore they can combine with another
witness.
Why won't he be precise enough to say the first מרדאות? marda'ot?
So you're giving them an example of two and three?
Oh, I don't know. That- I don't know why. That's a good
question. Like why we're assuming high- you know, that high off the
horizon. I don't know enough to answer that. תנו רבנן Tanu Rabbanan
ראינוהו במים, re'inuhu bamayim, we saw its reflection in the water. ראינוהו
בעששית, re'inuhu ba'ashashit, or we saw it through like a glass or
a lantern. ראינוהו בעבים, re'inuhu be'avim, or we saw it in the
clouds. אין מעידים עליו, ein me'idim alav, that's not enough because you
know you might see some glowing and you might be confusing it.
חציו במים חציו בעבים חציו בעששית אין מעידים עליו. chetzyo bamayim chetzyo
be'avim chetzyo ba'ashashit ein me'idim alav. Or they say we saw half
of it in the clouds or half of it in the reflection.
It's no good. So the גמרא Gemara says one minute, השתא כולו
אמרת לא? hashta kulo amrat lo? If you claim you saw all
of it, it's no good. חציו מיבעיא? chetzyo miba'ya? If you only
said half of it and you saw it in a reflection, of
course it's no good. No, אלא הכי קאמר. ela hachi ka'amar.
חציו במים חציו ברקיע. chetzyo bamayim chetzyo barakia. They're not saying they
just saw half. We saw half in the sky, but the other
half we only saw reflected. Or I'm not exactly sure how that
play- would be, but the other part is easy to understand. חציו
בעבים חציו ברקיע, chetzyo be'avim chetzyo barakia, we saw half directly and
half covered in clouds. חציו בעששית חציו ברקיע, chetzyo ba'ashashit chetzyo barakia,
we saw half through a glass and half in the sky. אין
מעידים. ein me'idim. Even that's not good. You have to see it
without any- without any, you know, sort of interruption. Otherwise we're concerned
that you saw some glowing, you didn't exactly see the moon. תנו
רבנן Tanu Rabbanan ראינוהו ושוב לא ראינוהו, re'inuhu v'shuv lo re'inuhu, אין
מעידים עליו. ein me'idim alav. We saw it, but then we didn't-
couldn't see it anymore. You can't testify. So the גמרא Gemara? says
one minute, כל הכי חזו ליה ואזיל? kol hachi chazu lei v'azil?
What, they have to see it non-stop? Besides which, the point is
is that the new moon is only visible for a few minutes.
Right? This is the new moon. It's visible for a few minutes
after sunset and then it sets. So of course you saw it
and then you didn't see it. I mean, what- what else happens?
So the גמרא Gemara says, אמר אביי הכי קאמר amar Abaye hachi
ka'amar ראינוהו מאלינו, re'inuhu me'aleinu,
we saw it just like in passing. We weren't- oh you know,
like incidentally we saw it. ושבנו לראותו מדעתנו, v'shavnu l'ro'oto mida'ateinu, and
then we went back and tried to say hey, we can testify
to it. Let's go check it out again, make sure that's what
we saw. ולא ראינוהו, v'lo re'inuhu, and then when we tried to
look at it in- like intentionally to testify about it, we couldn't
see it. אין מעידים עליו. ein me'idim alav. You can't testify. מאי
טעמא? mai ta'ama? What's the reason? אמר כובישא דעיבא בעלמא הוא דחזא.
amar kuvisha de'eiva b'alma hu d'chaza. Maybe they just saw like a
little round cloud. Okay, so obviously you don't have to see it
non-stop, and you only have a few minutes to see it, and
it didn't say that you can only testify if you saw it
with intent to testify. That's an interesting גמרא Gemara discussion that comes
up in מכות Makkot and in other places about whether you witness
something, do you have to intend to witness it in order to
testify? It doesn't say that. But it does say that if you
had a little bit of a doubt and you wanted to say
let's double check and make sure we know what we- They saw
and then you couldn't see it, so there we have to assume
that you didn't see what you thought you saw. Okay. So that
seems to be the point. But if they, if they had stopped
at stage one and said, oh look at that! We saw the
moon, let's go testify, presumably that would be fine. But the fact
that they went back to double-check and then they couldn't see it,
that's the problem. Okay. Moving on. ראש בית דין אומר מקודש. Rosh
Beis Din omer mekudash. So that was a little bit more about
what we expect them to say. We're not done with that, but
we're a little more astronomy and now we get to the process
of what do you call it, of the בית דין Beis Din
accepted the testimony and is now going to officially sanctify the new
month. So, ראש בית דין אומר מקודש, Rosh Beis Din omer mekudash,
the head of the court says sanctified. וכל העם עונים אחריו מקודש
מקודש, vechol ha'am onim acharav mekudash mekudash,
and everybody else repeats, sanctified, sanctified. So it shows basically something that
is done by the person in charge, the head, the person who
represents the Jewish community. I mean, this is the Jewish community essentially,
right, establishing the calendar. So the idea of this ritual of them
responding I think is powerful because it's basically saying like they are,
because it's the idea of אשר תקראו אותם asher tikre'u osam as
the גמרא Gemara will say, "You the people get to figure out
the calendar." So yes, our representative is doing it, but that sense
of the verbalizing our assent and our acceptance of it is very
powerful and that this is what now creates the communal calendar.
And it's also with the עדים eidim also, right?
Because that's what... Yeah. I mean, you don't go around... עם, am,
okay, but whoever is there, whoever is present, but at least it's
symbolically significant. Okay. בין שנראה בזמנו בין שלא נראה בזמנו מקדשין אותו,
bein shenireh bizmano bein shelo nireh bizmano mekadeshin oso, whether it was
seen again בזמנו, bizmano, which means on day 30, so the previous
month was a short month, or whether not, you do the same
case. Meaning, even though if it was not a short month by
day 31, you know which day is ראש חודש, Rosh Chodesh, you
don't need this, it'll obviously be ראש חודש, Rosh Chodesh, but to
emphasize the fact that we the people
are the ones designating the calendar, you want to do that act
even when it's self-evident which day is ראש חודש. Rosh Chodesh. Look,
it's also self-evident which year is the יובל Yovel year if you've
been counting 49 years. And nevertheless, there's a מצוה mitzvah of וקדשתם
את שנת החמישים שנה. ve-kidashtem es shnas ha-chamishim shana. It's not just
because you don't know, it's to actually emphasize you are creating it
and sanctifying it. Okay. So here too, בין שנראה בזמנו בין שלא
נראה בזמנו מקדשין אותו. bein shenireh bizmano bein shelo nireh bizmano mekadeshin
oso. רבי אלעזר ברבי צדוק אומר אם לא נראה בזמנו אין מקדשין
אותו שכבר קידשוהו שמים. Rabbi Elazar be-Rabbi Tzadok omer im lo nireh
bizmano ein mekadeshin oso she-kvar kidshuhu shamayim. Now, if it was not
seen in its time, it's a 30-day month, then you do not
do it because already by objectively the next day is ראש חודש
Rosh Chodesh and therefore there's no need for you to do anything
to make it ראש חודש. Rosh Chodesh. Okay. By the way, think
about שבת, Shabbos, right? זכור את יום השבת לקדשו. zachor es yom
ha-Shabbos le-kadsho. So that's קידוש השמים, kidush ha-shamayim, that's it's going to
be שבת Shabbos whether I say קידוש Kiddush or not, but there's
an idea of adding to it a level of my sanctifying of
it and designating of it. So that's the opinion of the תנא
קמא. Tanna Kamma. Let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara ראש
בית דין מנא הני מילי, Rosh Beis Din mana hanei milei, where
do you get this idea that you say מקודש mekudash and the
people answer? אמר חזקיה בר גמדא אמר רבי יוסי בן שאול אמר
רבי אמר קרא, amar Chizkiyah bar Gamda amar Rabbi Yossi ben Shaul
amar Rabbi amar kra, a verse said, וידבר משה את מועדי ה'
אל בני ישראל. Vayidaber Moshe es mo'adei Hashem el bnei Yisrael. So
Moshe declared, not just communicated the laws, but declared the מועדים. mo'adim.
מכאן שראש בית דין אומר מקודש. mikan she-Rosh Beis Din omer mekudash.
So Moshe represents the head of the court, the representative of the
people,
and he is the one that first declares it to the people.
So he says מקודש. mekudash. All right. וכל העם עונים אחריו מקודש
מקודש, vechol ha'am onim acharav mekudash mekudash, everybody responds. מנלן? menalan? אמר
רב פפא אמר קרא, amar Rav Pappa amar kra, אשר תקראו אותם,
asher tikre'u osam, these are the days that you will declare them.
So, and you've already pointed to the fact that תקראו tikre'u is
in the plural, but the גמרא Gemara's does another point: קרי ביה
אתם, keri beih atem, אשר תקראו אתם. asher tikre'u atem. You should
declare them. Is it missing a ו? vav?
No,
no, it's a play on words. You the people must declare. We
the people. רב נחמן בר יצחק אמר אלה הם מועדי. Rav Nachman
bar Yitzchak amar eileh heim mo'adai. הם יאמרו מועדי, heim yomru mo'adai,
הם מועדי. heim mo'adai. They should say it's my מועדים. mo'adim. So
again, this idea of it's not just from above, the people themselves
have to
assent to what's declared and be part of this declaration. All right.
מקודש מקודש תרי זימני למה לי, mekudash mekudash terei zimnei lama li,
why twice? דכתיב מקראי קודש. de-chsiv mikra'ei kodesh. מקראי, mikra'ei, callings, a
pluralness. Also like a way of saying אמן, amen, right? אמן אמן,
amen amen, מקודש מקודש. mekudash mekudash. It just really asserts the sense
of assenting. Oh, it doesn't have a ו? vav? Oh, יישר כוח,
shkoyach, okay, I didn't realize that. So Michael points out that אשר
תקראו אתם, asher tikre'u atem, it's not just the play, the ו
vav actually... I mean it is still a play, but the ו
vav is actually missing. Right. So that's a nice point. I didn't
realize that. Okay.
So the גמרא Gemara, goes on... so somebody once tried to say,
I don't know if this is בבא מעשיות bubba ma'asiyos or true,
but in the way we do the קידוש החודש kiddush hachodesh we
say, what's the line that we say, it says, it's right over
here... right over here...
yeah, all right, over there. So the line in
the...
because the idea of people try to say... The idea of doing
the קידוש החודש kiddush hachodesh in the שול shul is a type
of a reenacting of the קידוש החודש. kiddush hachodesh. ברכת החודש birkas
hachodesh is a type of a reenactment. Of course it's not, it's
a few days before, it's not the day that it would be
seen, but okay that's when everybody's in the שול. shul. So somebody
declares it, ראש חודש יהא ביום, Rosh Chodesh yihei hayom, which is
sort of like in place of, right, in place of the מקודש
מקודש, mekudash mekudash, but somebody wanted to say once it says חברים
כל ישראל ונאמר אמן, Chaveirim kol Yisroel venomar amen, that that was
like
first like somehow indicating this two stages,
that חברים Chaveirim and then כל ישראל ונאמר אמן. kol Yisroel venomar
amen. Like different everybody is assenting to. Of course I don't know
if it really works because the sage says מי שעשה נסים לאבותינו,
Mi she'asa nissim la'avoseinu, it's not really about the acknowledging of it
as ראש חודש, Rosh Chodesh, if anything that should have come after
the person announces it. But anyway you have this idea of it
being announced and then everybody assenting to it.
רבי אלעזר בר צדוק אומר אם לא נראה בזמנו אין מקדשין אותו.
Rabbi Eliezer bar Tzadok omer im lo nira bizmano ein mekadeshin oso.
תניא Tanya פלימו אומר בזמנו אין מקדשין אותו, Plimo omer bizmano ein
mekadeshin oso, if it's a short month you do not sanctify it.
שלא בזמנו מקדשין אותו, Shelo bizmano mekadeshin oso, only if it's a
long month you sanctify it. I cannot begin to understand that. רש"י
Rashi says שאינו צריך חיזוק, she'aino tzarich chizuk, that then it's like
it doesn't need חיזוק. chizuk. I don't know why it doesn't need
חיזוק. chizuk. Anyway he says maybe you already accepted the witnesses or
accepting the witnesses makes it clear enough. That's a very, very bizarre
position. I can't explain it. רבי אלעזר בר שמעון אומר בין כך
ובין כך אין מקדשין אותו. Rabbi Eliezer bar Shimon omer bein kach
uvein kach ein mekadeshin oso. Now here's a, so basically we're going
to get all four possibilities, okay? We had two in the משנה,
mishnah here the other two. So this one is you don't have
to do it either way, you accept the witnesses but you don't
do this ritual act of
מקדשין. mekadshin. שנאמר וקדשתם את שנת החמישים שנה, shenemar Vekidashtem es shnas
hachamishim shana, שנים אתה מקדש, shanim ata mekadesh, you sanctify the years,
the יובל yovel year, ואי אתה מקדש חודשים, ve'i ata mekadesh chodashim,
there's no act of ritually sanctifying. You accept the witnesses and then
it clarifies what is being done. Now by the way that is
quite interesting because the absence of doing קידוש, kiddush, first of all
you could say like it's like just as a good way of
the people acknowledging it and just a, you know what day, like
informing the people, not only informing the people but like sort
of about like implicitly reaffirming or establishing the
fact that you have the power to do it. Like if you
get up and say מקודש mekudash and everybody says מקודש מקודש, mekudash
mekudash, you know it's sort of it very much sends the message,
internalizes the message, בית דין Beis Din declares ראש חודש, Rosh Chodesh,
that's their power to do it and so on. By not doing
it besides that like it's not a concrete event that people will
now acknowledge as easily when day was ראש חודש, Rosh Chodesh, you
would also think that it sort of a little bit undermines the
power of בית דין. Beis Din. The argument though could be somewhat
of the opposite. The argument could be that although I do think
this is undermining the power of בית, Beis, that if you see
what בית דין Beis Din is doing is really just identifying what
the astronomical realities are, not that they are empowered to declare ראש
חודש, Rosh Chodesh, you know they check certain evidence but they then
make ראש חודש. Rosh Chodesh. No they don't make ראש חודש, Rosh
Chodesh, ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh is made based on the astronomical realities.
They just clarify what those astronomical realities are, so then there's not
going to be this act of מקודש מקודש mekudash mekudash because they're
not the ones creating ראש חודש, Rosh Chodesh, it's created naturally based
on the astronomical realities. So that could be why he doesn't have
them saying it, but bottom line is the whole thrust of this
entire מסכת masechet is that no, בית דין Beis Din is empowered
and they can ignore the עדים eidim if they want to, they
can do it on a different day if they want to. You
know, so do you really want to be not highlighting בית דין's
Beis Din power and not doing this ritual מקודש מקודש? mekudash mekudash?
So again another very strange position here, not as not as, you
know, ironic as פלימו's Plimo but still a strange one that you
would not have them do it at all. אמר רב יהודה אמר
שמואל amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel says רב יהודה אמר שמואל Rav
Yehuda amar Shmuel הלכה halacha כרבי אלעזר בר צדוק, k'Rabbi Eliezer bar
Tzadok, we rule like רבי אלעזר בר צדוק Rabbi Eliezer bar Tzadok
that you only do it on a twenty-nine day month, not on
a thirty day month. אמר אביי amar Abaye אף אנן נמי תנינא,
af anan nami tanina, we taught similarly, ראוהו בית דין וכל ישראל
נחקרו העדים ולא הספיקו לומר מקודש עד שחשכה הרי זה מעובר. ra'uhu
Beis Din vechol Yisroel nechkeru ha'eidim velo hispiku lomar mekudash ad shechashecha
harei ze me'ubar. So this is the משנה mishnah. coming up. The
בית דין Beis Din saw it and everybody saw it, it was
like visible to the entire people and they went through the process
and they investigated the witnesses and they did not have the chance
to say the magic words מקודש mekudash until it grew dark, so
it's not מקודש, mekudash, it's not a twenty-nine day month, it's a
מעובר. me'ubar. That's a later משנה. Mishna, So what are we going
to infer from this? מעובר אין מקודש לא. me'ubar in mekudash lo.
It says that when you blew it and now it's a thirty
day month because you didn't do it in time, it says it's
automatically מעובר. me'ubar. It doesn't say something like oh you blew it
so now you'll have to be מקדש mekadesh the next day, right?
הרי זה יקדשוהו למחר harei ze yekadshuhu lemachar is what it could
have said. It doesn't say יקדשוהו למחר, yekadshuhu lemachar, it says הרי
זה מעובר. harei ze me'ubar. So you see that automatically it's מעובר
me'ubar you don't say the מקודש mekudash on the following day. Okay
one minute, the גמרא Gemara's says לא מעובר איצטריכא ליה. lo me'ubar
itztiricha lei. No it had to use the phrase הרי זה מעובר.
harei ze me'ubar. It couldn't say the phrase יקדשוהו למחר, yekadshuhu lemachar,
why not? סלקא דעתך אמינא, salka da'atach amina, I might have thought
since the בית Beis saw it... Israel, איפרסמא. isparsema. So maybe it's
so public that you are forced now to have to do it
even though you blew it and you didn't do it on day
thirty, maybe you'll have to do ולא יעברוהו, ve'lo ya'abruhu, you won't
make it a thirty day month because every it's so obvious you
have to see to everybody's perception and you have to make it
a twenty-nine day month even if you blew it, even if you
missed the right day. קמשמלן Kamashmalan that no, you live with it
and you make it a thirty day month. Now by the way,
okay, that's all very nice, that's פשט pshat of the משנה, Mishna
פשט pshat of the משנה Mishna, is you're stuck and it's a
thirty day month, but what does that matter whether you use the
phrase of הרי זה מעובר harei ze meubar or use another phrase
of יקדשוהו למחר? yekadshuhu lemachar? So Rashi says that this is very
important because this is going to be a little shocking to you,
but this is also the position of Rambam. Rashi says if it
had said יקדשוהו למחר, yekadshuhu lemachar, you know how you might have
interpreted that? You wait till the next day, and the next day
you do what? You sanctify which day? The previous day. If it
had said יקדשוהו למחר, yekadshuhu lemachar, I might have read it like,
oh, everybody knows that the moon was seen today, so even if
we blew it and didn't get it done today, maybe we'll wait
till tomorrow and sanctify the previous day. קמשמלן, Kamashmalan, therefore it can't
say יקדשוהו למחר yekadshuhu lemachar because that might have communicated that idea,
and therefore it says מעובר meubar to clearly communicate that no, you
blew it, it's a thirty day month. Now you could say according
to Rashi that means that okay, קמשמלן kamashmalan is you can't sanctify
it late and do it retroactively. But Rambam actually rules, and we'll
see this possibility coming up in a later משנה, Mishna, that it
actually is possible on a later day to retroactively sanctify an earlier
day, that on day thirty-one you could retroactively sanctify day thirty. Okay,
presumably assuming that the witnesses are telling you that and so on.
So anyway, that's why it had to say הרי זה מעובר. harei
ze meubar. Okay, but bottom line is it's not clear how we
rule from the משנה, but the claim is that we rule like
רבי אלעזר בר שמעון, Rebbi Elazar bar Shimon, רבי אלעזר בר צדוק
Rebbi Elazar bar Tzadok that
you only do מקודש מקודש mikudash mikudash on a twenty-nine day month,
not a thirty day month.
Yes. ירושלמי Yerushalmi seems to think that you say מקודש mikudash even
for a thirty day after a thirty day.
Yeah, I mean the discussion is not closed. Okay, that was a
debate in the תנאים, Tannaim, it's still a debate of how we
actually rule.
I was going to say something similar, it's strange that on the
thirtieth day you don't say מקודש היום, mikudash hayom, right? The same
way that they didn't want to say nothing with the משואות. massu'ot.
Right. Right, why is it completely parallel in the mind of the
גמרא? Gemara.
Well, it does according to, well, according to רבי אלעזר בר צדוק
Rebbi Elazar bar Tzadok it is completely parallel. You do מקודש mikudash
on day if it's a twenty-nine day month and not a thirty
day month, which exactly parallels what they would do with the torches.
Right?
But what if you so to speak, if you can say you
blew it, so it's מעובר, meubar, it's a thirty day
month. Why not make the announcement on the thirtieth day?
I agree, but on the other hand, you don't need בית דין
Beis Din now, it's automatically if twenty-nine if for the
purposes of publicizing to the population.
Right, so the publicizing can happen apart from the ritual of setting
the day.
Ah, just get the word out.
Yeah, exactly. Get the word out without doing the ritual. Okay. Now
going back to testing the witnesses and exactly what they saw, so
without getting into astronomical details, we get into other questions
about what they would use to test them. So let's take a
look.
דמות צורות לבנה היו לו לרבן גמליאל בטבלא ובכותל עלייתו. Demut tzurot
levana hayu lo l'Rabban Gamliel b'tabla u'v'kotel aliyato. So images of the
moon, Rabban Gamliel would have in his, now this is not, this
is רבן גמליאל דיבנה, Rabban Gamliel d'Yavne, not רבן גמליאל הזקן, Rabban
Gamliel Hazaken, in on a טבלא tabla and like you know and
on the wall in his attic. שבהן מראה את הדיוטות, Shebahen mareh
et hedyotot, he would show the laypeople ואומר הכזה ראית או כזה.
v'omer hakezeh ra'ita o kazeh. So like when you go for your
eye exam. Does it look like this or like this? Does it
look better? הכזה ראית או כזה. Hakezeh ra'ita o kazeh.
So anyway, he would ask them, it's a lot easier to show
with pictures than it is to describe with words. Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara. says like this. ומי שרי? U'mi shari? Since when are
you allowed to have images of the moon? והכתיב, Ve'hakativ, the verse
says
לא תעשון אתי, lo ta'asun iti, you shall not make with me,
so we'll see what that means, לא תעשון כדמות שמשיי, lo ta'asun
kidmut shamshai, do not make like those things that attend to me,
those my attendants, presumably the celestial bodies. Don't make images of the
celestial bodies. אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, Abaye says no, לא אסרה תורה
אלא שמשים שאפשר לעשות כמותן. lo asra Torah ela shamashim she'efshar la'asot
kemotan. The only thing you're not allowed to make are things that
are attend to God as it were that are really replicable. You
can't make a moon, you make a model of a moon, but
you can't really make the moon. So what are the things that
are really replicable? כדתניא, Kidtanya, like we taught in a ברייתא. braita.
לא יעשה אדם בית תבנית היכל, Lo ya'aseh adam bayis tavnit heichal,
a
person should not make his house to look like the היכל Heichal
in the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, אכסדרה תבנית אולם, achsadra tavnit ulam,
or you should not make your אכסדרה, achsadra, your portico, to look
like the אולם, Ulam, which was the entrance hall to the היכל.
Heichal. חצר כנגד עזרה, Chatzer keneged azara, you should not make your
courtyard to be the exact parameters of the temple courtyard. שולחן כנגד
שולחן, Shulchan keneged shulchan, and you cannot make a table, your table,
to look like the שולחן Shulchan in the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash.
מנורה כנגד מנורה, Menorah keneged menorah, or your candelabrum like the מנורה.
Menorah. אבל עושה, Aval oseh, but you could... של חמישה ושל שישה
ושל שמונה. shel chamisha v'shel shisha v'shel shemona.
You could make a מנורה Menorah five or six or eight arms,
של שבעה לא יעשה, shel shiva lo ye'aseh, and but of seven
arms you cannot make a מנורה Menorah even of other metals, even
if it's not gold,
because presumably the same shape. Right? That's always a question of how
similar are we talking about? Presumably those the same shape. There is
some, one אחרון Acharon that wants to say, you know the old
question the בית יוסף Beis Yosef asks, which is why is חנוכה
Chanukah eight days since the oil itself could have lasted one, the
miracle was only seven days? So some say, oh, because they had
that seven days and you would have had a bit of a
less making a מנורה Menorah with seven arms. שולן shuls all over
America have מנורות. Menorahs. Right? I know, I know.
There's a gold מנורה Menorah in the Cardo.
All right, so let me read it and then we can talk
a little bit more. One minute, one minute. Let's just read a
little bit more. So even of other metals because the מנורה Menorah
itself could be made of other metals. רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה אומר,
Rebbi Yosef berabi Yehuda omer, אף של עץ לא יעשה. af shel
eitz lo ye'aseh. Not only metals, you can't even make it out
of wood, כדרך שעשו בית חשמונאי, k'derech she'asu Beis Chashmonai, because the
מנורה Menorah was once made out of wood when they entered into
the temple in the time of חנוכה Chanukah and they didn't have,
the מנורה Menorah had been stolen or and therefore they had to
remake a מנורה Menorah and they made it out of wood spears.
So you see you can make it out of wood. אמרו לו,
Amru lo, they said back to him, no, משם ראיה? misham raya?
You want to bring a proof from there? שפודין של ברזל היו,
shfudin shel barzel hayu, those weren't wood, those were iron spears, וחיפום
בבעץ vechifum b'va'atz
and they were covered with lead, so therefore maybe they looked a
little bit wooden, they were dull metal, and but they were not
wood, but a מנורה Menorah has to be out of metal. העשירו,
He'ashiru, and once they got rich ועשאום משל כסף v'asu m'shel kesef
and they made them silver, חזרו והעשירו עשאום משל זהב chazru v'he'ashiru
asu m'shel zahav and eventually they made them out of gold. So
that's the debate whether a מנורה Menorah has to be out of
metal or can it be even out of wood. By the way,
תוספות Tosafot points out, take a look at תוספות, Tosafot, שפודין של
ברזל, shfudin shel barzel, האי דקרי לה שפודין, hai d'kari lei shfudin,
why is it called, you know, spears or poles? משום שלא היו
גביעים כפתורים ופרחים אלא אם כן בזהב. mishum shelo hayu g'vi'im kaftorim
u'frachim ela im kein b'zahav. Because all of the ornamentation that the
Torah demands for מנורות Menorahs is only if it's gold. If it's
not gold, then you don't need that ornamentation, which means on the
flip side, that it's easier to transgress this prohibition of making a
replica because all you really need is, you know, seven. And again
by the way Michael, your issue about the shape, if they just
put seven spears in the ground, right, that's not the shape in
the Torah. Now the bigger question is it's not one unit, so
how would like can you have seven separate spears? But anyway but
this then becomes the question of does it have to look exactly
like they did it in the temple? It has to be something
that could presumably qualify for the temple, which makes it a much
broader category of what exactly, you know, what exactly is considered a
replica. So this becomes a big issue. For example, when they made
the whole, you know, temple model which they have in where the
Holyland Hotel, right? So how you allowed to do that? So we'll
see in the end of this גמרא Gemara about a different thing
that the גמרא Gemara says אתם עשו להבין ולהורות atem asu l'havin
u'lehorot by a different concern. Maybe that's valid there. Maybe you could
say it's so small it's not usable, that's a model, it's not
life-size, right? Every kid that does a פרשה Parsha project on, you
know, on תרומה Truma and whatever and goes and makes little models
of the thing. So that's also one thing that if it's not
like usable. The question about like the temple people, what's their name?
The Temple Institute, you know, I think I told you this story
before about the בגדי כהונה. Bigdei Kehuna. I once said to them,
how do you make this? What about the איסור issur of making
a replica? And they said to me, it's not a replica, we're
going to use it! But okay,
but I don't know, do Orthodox שולן shuls have seven-candled seven-armed מנורות?
Menorahs?
I don't think Orthodox
שולן shuls have
seven arms. Interesting. But not with candles, but with incandescent lights usually.
Huh. Interesting, yeah.
You know, every, every Moderox scholar goes to בית אלפא Beit Alpha
and they see on the mosaic floor, ah, you see they incorporated,
you know, idolatrous imagery. So this ברייתא Beraita suggests that the, that
this פסוק pasuk in the עשרת הדיברות Aseret HaDibrot only not only
has to, well
we're not done.
This is one thing. We're going to keep on adding to the
list of things you're not allowed to do.
So right now we're saying that it's okay to make the moon,
just don't make the היכל, Heichal, whatever.
So correct, so correct, but we're not done. So the answer right
now is as long as you don't make the things you can
really make replicas of like the בית המקדש, Beit Hamikdash, you're allowed
to make them. And not to worship obviously, but to have them
as images. But we're not done. So the גמרא Gemara says ושמשים
שאפשר לעשות כמותם מי שרי? v'shamashim she'efshar la'asot k'mosam mi'shari?
I don't get it, you do mean attendants, שמשים shamashim to God,
you know things that are related to God that you are not,
you cannot make an exact replica of is allowed? Is that really
true? והתניא דתניא ברייתא, v'hatanya d'tanya Beraita, לא תעשון אתי, lo ta'asun
iti, so do not make with Me, those things with Me, לא
תעשון כדמות שמשי המשמשים לפני במרום. lo ta'asun kidmut shamashai hameshamshim lifanai
b'marom.
The things that My attendants that serve Me up in the celestial
spheres. What does that mean? So it's explicit. כמשמשים לפני במרום. k'mishamshim
lifanai b'marom.
The celestial bodies, not just the temple. You cannot make images of
those. So
אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, says אביי, Abaye, לא אסרה תורה אלא דמות
ארבעה
פנים בהדי הדדי. lo asra Torah ela d'mut arba'ah panim bahadi hadadei.
פני אחד אדם פני אחד אריה פני אחד, pnei echad adam pnei
echad aryeh pnei echad,
right?
So only that celestial being is the one thing you can't do.
Other types of things you can do. By the way, I should
stop to note that the temple issue is a little bit different
than this, but the idea of שמשים המשמשים לפניי shamashim hameshamshim lefanai
is a different concern than what we normally, or it is an
עבודה זרה avoda zara concern, but different than what we normally think
about. When we normally think about עבודה זרה, avoda zara, we think
about an image of a different god, Zeus, and you're going to
worship Zeus. Okay, but part of the Torah's concern of עבודה זרה
avoda zara is trying to create something that represents God and worship
God through that. So when, for example, the Torah says, פן תשחתון
ועשיתם לכם, pen tashchitun va'asitem lachem, you know, what's it say, השמרו
לכם פן, hishamru lachem pen, כי לא ראיתם כל תמונה ביום דיבר
ה' אלהיכם עמכם בחורב מתוך האש, ki lo re'item kol tmuna beyom
diber Hashem eloheichem imachem bechorev mitoch ha'esh, right?
Pay careful heed that you did not see any image at Mount
Sinai. פן תשחתון ועשיתם לכם פסל תמונת כל סמל, pen tashchitun va'asitem
lachem pesel tmunat kol samel, unless you make yourself an image. What
are you going to make an image of? Not of a different
god. You're going to think that you saw something at Mount Sinai
and try to recapture that and make an image and worship God
as through that or that as a representation of God. So that's
another type of עבודה זרה avoda zara concern. That was the question
of whether that was חטא העגל chet ha'egel maybe, not a different
god but a way of embodying God. So these are the concerns
of do not try to make images of those things that attend
to me as a way of worshipping me, and that's how it
is understanding this prohibition. But אביי Abaye is limiting this only to
that type of like celestial angel, a very specific type of a
thing. Just one minute, so let's see what the גמרא Gemara answer
is.
אלא מעתה, ela me'ata, says גמרא, Gemara if that's true, פרצוף אדם
לחודיה תישתרי, partzuf adam lechudei tisharei, so then it would be permissible
to make the face of a human. אלמה תניא, alama tanya, why
do we teach in a ברייתא, braita, כל הפרצופות מותרין, kol hapartzufot
mutarin, all faces are permissible, חוץ מפרצוף אדם, chutz mipartzuf adam,
except for the human face. Now by the way, that ברייתא braita
in its initial location is in the context of keeping a vessel
that was discarded that you found and whether you have to be
concerned that it was this done for ornamentation or done for worship.
But תוספות Tosafot says, and we're not going to get into the
details, but here the גמרא Gemara assuming that it's also related to
the issue of making. So you can make faces of animals, but
you cannot make the face of a human. So according to you,
if, right, why is it only—you said only the four-faced angel is
prohibited. So why is a human face prohibited? So אמר רב הונא
בריה דרב אידי מפרקי דאביי שמיע לי, amar Rav Huna brei deRav
Idi mipirkei deAbaye shmi'a li, I heard from אביי Abaye's sort of
teaching, לא תעשון אתי, lo ta'asun iti, another דרשה drasha that excludes
a human face. לא תעשון אותי, lo ta'asun oti, do not make
me. So why is a human face me? Because, well, no, because
presumably because of צלם אלהים. tzelem Elokim. So making the image of
the human and the face really represents the human,
our human distinctness. So the human face is a representation of God,
a representation of something created בצלם אלהים. betzelem Elokim. That's a very
powerful statement in the גמרא. Gemara But now what you have is
you cannot make the things that are replicas of the temple, you
cannot make the heavenly angel that is described in the beginning of
ישעיהו, Yeshayahu, four faces, and you can't make a human face. But
sun, moon, and stars, that's still okay. Now somebody is going to
ask, wait a minute, if you can't make a human face, then
why do you have to tell me I can't make the four-faced
angel since one of those faces is a human face? So תוספות
Tosafot says good question. So תוספות Tosafot says well, let's say somebody
else had made the human face and you now want to take
it and finish making the other three faces. That you can't do
either. So but it does become a little superfluous to prohibit that.
But we are limiting it to human, temple, and a very particular
type of angel. All other things would be allowed, presumably.
Yeah, a question is, you know, we're saying making a human face,
it's very different than like painting it versus sculpting it.
Okay, that's an excellent question which I am—excellent question, excellent question. So
that is discussed, you know, not here. A little bit תוספות Tosafot
alludes to it. There's other גמרות Gemaras which discuss it more at
length and that is a big big question למעשה lemaaseh about whether
we're talking about two-dimensional or three-dimensional. Some want to say that the—well
because we're going to get around to making it a problem of
drawing the celestial, you know, the sun, moon, and stars. And some
want to say that because we only see it as two dimensions,
it's prohibited to do even two dimensions. Whereas the human face that
we see in three dimensions is only—to do it two-dimensional would not
be a real representation, would be allowed. Okay, of course the thing
is is that as we know, traditionally Jews have been much more
reluctant to draw a human image even two-dimensional than they have been
to draw like a picture of a sun. Right, what happens? I
mean, here right over here, have I been over on this איסור
issur ten times right now? Your kid comes home with a little
picture, right, sun and
flowers, so are you
telling me I can't do this?
Right, there you go, I was just
over on לא תעשון אתי. lo ta'asun iti.
Okay, so
that's the eleventh, that's the eleventh.
What?
That's the eleventh עבירה.
aveira. What?
That's the eleventh one there. Oh, the eleventh עבירה. Aveira. Of the
ten over here, right. Anyway, so that's the real question: what, two
dimensions, three dimensions, and how much of a representation is considered a
representation? So anyway, let's read a little bit more in the גמרא.
Gemara Okay, so but now we only have humans, a particular type
of angels, and the temple. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like
this: שאר שמשי מי שרי? Shaar shamashay misharay? One minute, are other
attendants permitted? והתניא, V'ha tanya, we taught in a ברייתא, Baraita, לא
תעשון אתי, Lo Taasuni Itti, לא תעשון כדמות שמשי המשמשים לפני במרום,
Lo taasun kidmut shamshai hameshamshim lefanai bamrom, those things that attend to
me up in the spheres, and the celestial spheres, כגון, K'gon, אופנים
ושרפים וחיות הקודש ומלאכי השרת, Ofanim u'Srafim v'Chayot HaKodesh u'Malachei HaSharet, so
all images of angels are forbidden, like if you know what those,
how those look, but okay. אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, fine, לא אסרה
תורה אלא שמשי שבמדור העליון. Lo asra Torah ella shamshai shebimador haelyon.
Fine, but all those are on the upper, you know, the highest
sort of celestial sphere, those are forbidden, the angels, but the things
in the lower spheres, like the, you know, the planetary bodies and
the sun and the moon and the stars and those aren't a
problem. All right, so now it's not just the four-faced angel, it's
all the angels. But we still don't have the sun, moon, and
stars. So the גמרא Gemara says, ושל מדור התחתון מי שרי? V'shel
madur hatachton misharay? Since when are those things in the lower sphere
permitted? והתניא, V'tanya, we taught in a ברייתא, Baraita,
אשר בשמים, Asher bashamayim, it says right, אשר בשמים ממעל ואשר בארץ
מתחת, Asher bashamayim mimaal v'asher baaretz mitachat, right? So that's in the
עשרת הדברות. Aseret HaDibrot. That לא תעשון אתי Lo Taasuni Itti is
after the עשרת הדברות, Aseret HaDibrot, right? The in the עשרת הדברות,
Aseret HaDibrot, right, אשר בשמים ממעל Asher bashamayim mimaal is like, you
know, is about אלהים אחרים. Elohim acherim. Okay, so the, לא תעשה
לך פסל, Lo Taaseh lecha pesel, but it's right after אלהים אחרים,
Elohim acherim, it's a very different context. Until now these are things
associated with God. This is a פסוק Pasuk that is much more
anchored in worship of other gods. So let's see what the גמרא
Gemara does with it. אשר בשמים לרבות חמה ולבנה כוכבים ומזלות, Asher
bashamayim lerabot chamah ulevanah kochavim umazalot, the sun and the moon and
the stars and the constellations. ממעל לרבות מלאכי השרת, Mimaal lerabot malachei
hasharet, heavenly angels. So you see it's all אסור. Assur. Now, כי
תניא ההיא לעובדם. Ki tanya hahee l'ovdam.
Now, that's in the context of doing it for the purpose of
worshipping them. Again, rooted much more in עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah, that's
of course and that's why that's forbidden, but just for like, you
know, just for art, that's not a problem. So the גמרא Gemara
says one minute, אי לעובדם אפילו שלשול קטן נמי? Ee l'ovdam afilu
shilshul katan nami? If it's to worship then anything is forbidden to
make, even like a little worm. אין הכי נמי, Ein hachi nami,
you're right. תניא, Tanya, אשר בארץ לרבות הרים וגבעות ימים ונהרות אפיקים
וגאיות, Asher baaretz lerabot harim ugevaot yamim uneharot afikim v'geiot, so all
these various types of, you know, mountains and valleys etc., rivers and
oceans. מתחת Mitachat below לרבות שלשול קטן, lerabot shilshul katan, even a
tiny little worm. So, river. So anyway, so everything, yeah, you're right.
That פסוק Pasuk is not limiting it to angels and to sun,
moon and stars. If you look at the end of the דרשה,
Drasha, or you look at the end of the פסוק, Pasuk, it's
saying don't make anything. Okay, so we have something rooted in עבודה
זרה Avodah Zarah which is don't make anything with the purpose of
worshipping it. But we have these other things which are don't make
things connected to God even if you're not intending to worship it
just because it is too much like it's, you know, it's too
close for comfort.
Even with monotheistic motive,
not only monotheistic motivated, but even if you're not intending to worship
it, I just want to have a bust of a human, I
just want to have this, it looks nice, even if it's purely
for aesthetic and artistic reasons, if it's too close to God it
is, you know, it's like a type of a biblical גזירה, Gzera,
or it's too much what would be understood as an embodiment of
God even if your intent is not to worship it. Okay, so
in the... well, so if you are not, okay, so where are
we up to? To make something to worship, obviously everything is forbidden,
that's making an idol. To make something not to worship but you
cannot make things that are seen as too close to God, but
right now the only thing we forbidden is angels and human beings
and things related to the temple. Angels and human beings. But we're
still good about sun, moon and stars. But we're not done. Because
the גמרא Gemara says like this: ועשייה גרידתא מי
שרי? V'asiya gredata misharay? I mean just, but since when is just
making celestial bodies permissible, even not for the purpose of worshipping it?
דתניא, D'tanya, לא תעשון אתי, Lo Taasuni Itti, לא תעשון כדמות שמשי
המשמשים לפני, Lo taasun kidmut shamshai hameshamshim lefanai, do not make those
bodies that attend to me.
כגון חמה ולבנה כוכבים ומזלות, K'gon chamah ulevanah kochavim umazalot, so finally
linked to the פסוק Pasuk which we have been saying is not
about worship, it's just about making, it says explicitly do not make
things like the sun and the moon and the stars. So how
can you make it? So the גמרא Gemara says, שאני רבן גמליאל
דאחרים עשו לו. Shani Rabban Gamliel d'acherim asu lo. All right, he
got other people to do it for him. רש"י Rashi says non-Jews,
right.
Okay, so it's forbidden to have? No, it's just forbidden to make.
So he got somebody else to make it. So the גמרא Gemara
says, והא רב יהודה דאחרים עשו לו? V'ha Rav Yehuda d'acherim asu
lo? Wait a minute, רב יהודה Rav Yehuda had similarly had something
that was made, other people made for him. He had a signet
ring that had a human face on it. ואמר ליה שמואל, V'amar
lei Shmuel, and שמואל Shmuel said to him, רב יהודה, Rav Yehuda,
רב יהודה, Rav Yehuda, שינינא, Shinina, like sharp one, סמי עיניה דידיה,
Samei einei didey, so you know, rub out its eyes. you should
ruin the image so it doesn't look like a full human image.
That becomes this whole other question in art: can you make a
human image if it's not complete and complete, maybe if one of
the ears is covered with hair, you don't see all parts of
the image? How much does it, you know, at what stage is
it really considered to be a full image? Anyway, okay, anyway, as
you can imagine, this גמרא Gemara is a highly, highly relevant גמרא
Gemara for, you know, all these things we've been talking about. Anyway,
I mean, you know, for owning things, for making things, for art,
all those issues. Anyway, you see that someone else made the ring
and he wasn't allowed even to own it, that it should look
like the human image. So the גמרא Gemara says no. התם חותמו
בולט hatam chotamo bolet and
now we introduce the idea of three-dimensional.
There, if you didn't make it, the only issue about owning it
is that people will think it's an object of worship. The basic
problem is making. Don't make something close that's like connected to God,
that's like making an idol, even though that's not your intent. But
owning it, if it's only artistic is okay. But if it's three-dimensional,
there's a problem, a rabbinic problem that people might suspect you of
worshipping it.
כדתניא, kid-tanya, like we taught in the
ברייתא—now Baraita we're going to ask, but what about רבן גמליאל, Rabban
Gamliel, was his things two-dimensional or three-dimensional? We'll get to it. טבעת
חותמו בולט, tabaat chotamo bolet, if you have a ring that the
signet part, the seal, what's that called, the part that makes the
image? Anyway, the signet part is protruding, the what?
I know, I made it up.
Okay, anyway, protruding... what? Signet. Right. אסור להניחה, assur le-hanichah, you can't
wear it, because now you have a three-dimensional human face and because
people will suspect you of worshipping it. ומותר לחתום בה, u-mutar lachtom
bah, but you can use it to sign, to make your impression
in, because the impression will be indented. So that, right, if this
is protruding, the impression will be indented. You can use it for
that, but you can't wear it. But that's interesting because it also
sounds like if you're using it to make an impression, you are
owning it. It's just about wearing it. Anyway, חותמו שוקע, chotamo shokeia,
if it's indented, מותר להניחה, mutar le-hanichah, you can wear it, because
it's not protruding, ואסור לחתום בה, ve-assur lachtom bah, you can't use
it to sign, because then you will make a three-dimensional image. So
now what we have said is that if it's three-dimensional, as long
as you didn't make it, you're okay, but there's a problem of
people suspecting you. So now we're going to have to talk about
רבן גמליאל. Rabban Gamliel. By the way, the thing of a ring
might show that it's not just owning it, but owning it in
a way that you're connected to it, like it sounds like as
long as you don't wear the ring you're okay.
But anyway, the other issue though, so far the basic issue at
this point in making things is on artists and not on collectors.
Right. So now the גמרא Gemara says, ומי חיישינן לחשדא, u-mi chaishinan
le-chashada, are we really concerned about being suspected?
והא
בי כנישתא דשף ויתיב בנהרדעא, ve-ha be kenishta de-shaf ve-yasiv bi-nehardea, or
Shof ve-Yasiv, some people want to say it means that they, like,
you know, cleared out the rubble and rebuilt it, or maybe there's
even an understanding that they used the stones from the temple in
the בית המקדש Beis Ha-Mikdash to build it that were transported and
they built it with those stones. Anyway, there was a temple in
נהרדעא, Nehardea, דהוה ביה אנדרטא, de-havei beih andarta, there was a
statue, and havei, you know, not a statue for artistic purposes, והוה
אתו רב ושמואל ואבוה דשמואל ולוי ומצלו התם, va-havu atu Rav ve-Shmuel
ve-avuh de-Shmuel ve-Levi u-mitzlu hatam, and all these great rabbis went there
and they prayed there, ולא חיישי לחשדא, ve-lo chaishi le-chashada, nobody was
suspecting, they weren't concerned that people would suspect they were worshipping it,
and there they're actually going into a house of worship and they're
not concerned about suspicion. So the גמרא says no, רבים שאני. rabim
shani. Some place that's open for the masses, like, if everybody is
there, nobody suspects because, like, we all know what we're doing here
and I would never be worshipping an idol, if I'm going to
worship an idol, I'll do it in private, I'm not going to
do it in front of all you guys. So that's not a
context where there's a concern of חשד. chashad. So now the גמרא
says, ורבן גמליאל יחיד הוא, ve-Rabban Gamliel yachid hu, one minute, רבן
גמליאל Rabban Gamliel was not doing his thing in public, he had
a private, you know, meeting with the witnesses. So again, the גמרא
interestingly assumes that presumably that these are three-dimensional. Why did the גמרא
say רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel was three-dimensional? So here is where תוספות
Tosafot says, well, maybe the sun, moon, and stars, because they appear
two-dimensional, maybe it's a problem even two-dimensional for those, because otherwise the
גמרא could have said רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel maybe had two-dimensional, not
three-dimensional. But anyway, but that's just speculation. The גמרא is saying why
did רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel able to do it, he was an
individual? No, כיון דנשיא הוא שכיחי רבים גביה. keivan de-nasi hu shechichi
rabim gabei. No, you know, he was the נשיא, Nasi, so anyway,
his house was an open public space and therefore there was no
concern of חשד. chashad. אי בעית אימא, ee ba'is eima, and if
you want you could say, דפרקים הוה. de-prakim hava. Maybe it was
something that was, you know, different components that you would put together.
By the way, that is assuming
three-dimensional, right, דפרקים הוה. de-prakim hava. So for whatever reason, unlike תוספות,
Tosafot, you don't have to say it was two-dimensional and still a
problem. You could say the גמרא is assuming three-dimensional. But since it
was something that you would take apart and put together, presumably that
would not be a context of an object of worship. Of course,
the funny thing is, if you're taking apart and putting together, you're
sort of like making it. Anyway, ואיבעית אימא, ve-iba'it eima, if you
want you could say, לשלוט עביד, le-shlot avid, he did it in
order to—no, it's להתלמד עביד, le-is-lamad avid, he did it in order
to— For educational purposes, דכתיב dikhtiv לא תלמד לעשות, lo tilmad la'asot,
don't learn how to do like they
do, אבל אתה למד להבין ולהורות, aval ata lamed lehavin ulehorot, you
can learn in order to understand. Now the question is what is
that answering? Is that answering why biblically you're allowed to make it
even though it's prohibited, you can do it for educational purposes? Is
it answering the biblical problem and he actually didn't make it himself,
or are we back to the idea that somebody else made it,
but this idea that if it's educational purposes removes the rabbinic concern
of חשד? chashad? So there's a lot of things that obviously have
yet to be resolved. I do want to say one thing about
the חשד chashad issue, which is you know why are we allowed
to own like little dolls, you know, G.I. Joes or whatever those
types of things? You know, why isn't that an issue of חשד?
chashad? רב עובדיה יוסף Rav Ovadia Yosef says why can you have
like you know busts of faces and he says oh well not
you know in Iraq and all the Sephardic lands, you know, all
these wealthy Jews would have busts made of them and nobody ever
said anything. So okay, maybe because they were the wealthy Jews, but
okay. Anyway, he says he basically wants to say that if it's
all based on חשד chashad and you didn't make it, maybe even
things that the גמרא says fall in the חשד chashad category in
our contemporary circumstances and you know would not necessarily be חשד. chashad.
Nobody is חושד choshed you for worshipping your G.I. Joe, you know.
So therefore that raises interesting questions about owning art, even three-dimensional representational
art, right, where exactly how exactly חשד chashad plays out nowadays in
the area of ownership. But the biggest problem is the issue of
making it and particularly making things that are human form or of
the celestial bodies. And you know, Rav Kook has the famous letter
to the Bezalel Institute about the human form. But just to me,
like I said, you go home, you bring home something from second
grade that looks like this, why isn't that a prohibition? Right, again,
maybe it's three-dimensional, you know, but is the only issue, but exactly
what constitutes an image of these is still a little bit, is
still an open question. That's not according to תוספות. Tosafot. Yeah, well,
but that means...